Boker tov בוקר טוב, Boker tov,
we are on Masechet Shavuot מסכת שבועות, Masechet Shavuot, Daf Zayin דף
ז, Daf Zayin, and I actually would like to take us a
couple of lines earlier to the bottom of Vav amud bet ו
עמוד ב Vav amud bet so that we can start this unpacking
of this line in the Mishna משנה Mishna from the beginning. If
that's okay, we're in two, four, six, eight, ten, ten and a
half lines from the bottom of amud Vav, Daf Vav amud bet
דף ו עמוד ב: Daf Vav amud bet: et she-yesh bah yedi'ah
ba-techilah את שיש בה ידיעה בתחילה. et she-yesh bah yedi'ah ba-techilah. What
we're talking about, if you remember, we had four different ways of
knowing things. Not sure if we want to write this, it's a
little bit confusing when you just hear it in first time. Okay,
so we can have a situation where there's awareness in the beginning,
awareness in the end, and the ha-elem העלם ha-elem in the middle,
some no awareness in the middle. We can have awareness in the
beginning, no awareness at the end, no awareness in the beginning, knowledge
in the end, no awareness in the beginning, and no awareness in
the end. Okay? Does that, is that good? So these are four
options that the Mishna משנה Mishna was talking about. And now the
Mishna משנה Mishna is addressing et she-yesh bah yedi'ah ba-techilah את שיש
בה ידיעה בתחילה, et she-yesh bah yedi'ah ba-techilah, something that there is
awareness in the beginning, he'alem העלם, he'alem, some lack of awareness in
the middle, and then awareness again in the end. Why don't we
have the situation that there is awareness in the beginning and awareness
at the end and no lack of awareness in the middle?
I think a situation where we're fully aware of what we're doing
wrong at all times will be considered a Mezid מזיד, Mezid, not
something that has lack of awareness. Therefore it will fall into a
different category. Okay, so we're right now in the category of things
that we know we do not fully knowing what we're doing. And
the Torah throughout this upcoming amud עמוד amud and a half, like
Daf Zayin Alef דף ז א Daf Zayin Alef and some of
Bet ב, Bet, is going to base its words on Leviticus five,
the first five verses. So since the Gemara גמרא Gemara does not
bring it, I think it's maybe worthwhile to just look at it
quickly because we're going to keep referring back to it. Okay? So
the Leviticus in Vayikra Perek Hey ויקרא פרק ה Vayikra Perek Hey
in the beginning, it says, ve-nefesh ki techeta ve-sham'ah kol alah ve-hu
ed o ra'ah o yada im lo yagid ve-nasa avono ונפש כי
תחטא ושמעה קול אלה והוא עד או ראה או ידע אם לוא
יגיד ונשא עונו, ve-nefesh ki techeta ve-sham'ah kol alah ve-hu ed o
ra'ah o yada im lo yagid ve-nasa avono, o nefesh asher tiga
be-chol davar tame ונפש אשר תגע בכל דבר טמא, o nefesh asher
tiga be-chol davar tame, we will see that we're dealing with touching
things of tumah טומאה, tumah, o bi-nevelat chayah teme'ah o bi-nevelat behemah
teme'ah o bi-nevelat sheretz tame ve-ne'elam mimeno ve-hu tame ve-ashem או בנבלת
חיה טמאה או בנבלת בהמה טמאה או בנבלת שרץ טמא ונעלם ממנו
והוא טמא ואשם. o bi-nevelat chayah teme'ah o bi-nevelat behemah teme'ah o
bi-nevelat sheretz tame ve-ne'elam mimeno ve-hu tame ve-ashem. So this is somebody
who hears something, who is a witness and he doesn't say what
he's not testifying correctly,
o nefesh that touch or somebody who touches, a person that touches
any unclean thing, a carcass of a chayah חיה chayah or behemah
בהמה, behemah, we'll see the discussion about the difference between chayah חיה
chayah and behemah בהמה behemah and where they come together, ve-ne'elam mimeno
ונעלם ממנו, ve-ne'elam mimeno, it was, it escaped him, that fact escaped
him, he wasn't aware that he was doing it. And then he
was unclean, he realized his guilt. So at what time the yedi'ah
ידיעה yedi'ah came in, o ki tiga be-tum'at adam le-chol tum'ato asher
yitma bah ve-ne'elam mimeno ve-hu yada ve-ashem או כי תגע בטמאת אדם
לכל טמאתו אשר יטמא בה ונעלם ממנו והוא ידע ואשם. o ki
tiga be-tum'at adam le-chol tum'ato asher yitma bah ve-ne'elam mimeno ve-hu yada
ve-ashem. Or he touches a human uncleanness, any such uncleanness whereby one
becomes unclean, and though he has known it, that fact escaped him.
He knows that it's not okay to touch something unclean, but either
he wasn't aware when that happened, goes back, he's thinking, oh maybe
I touched something, maybe I didn't, I don't know what was going
on, and later he realizes his guilt. And then continuing, o nefesh
ki tishava levate bi-sfatayim le-hara או נפש כי תשבע לבטא בשפתים להרע.
o nefesh ki tishava levate bi-sfatayim le-hara. So this is our Masechet
מסכת Masechet
right, dealing with Shavuot שבועות, Shavuot, or someone, when a person utters
an oath le-hara o le-heitiv le-chol asher yevate ha-adam bi-shvuah ve-ne'elam mimeno
ve-hu yada ve-ashem le-achat me-eleh להרע או להיטיב לכל אשר יבטא האדם
בשבועה ונעלם ממנו והוא ידע ואשם לאחת מאלה.
le-hara o le-heitiv le-chol asher yevate ha-adam bi-shvuah ve-ne'elam mimeno
ve-hu yada ve-ashem le-achat me-eleh. To bad or good purpose, whatever a
man may utter an oath
for, and the closing, ve-hayah והיה, ve-hayah, this is later he. והיה
כי יאשם לאחת מאלה והתוודה אשר חטא עליה. vehaya ki yesham leachad
me'eleh vehitvada asher chata aleha. When he realizes his guilt in any
of these matters, he shall confess that he has sinned. Okay, we'll
keep this open. All right, so we'll go in to deal with
what are these פסוקים psukim doing in the middle of it? We're
talking about שבועות, shvuot, and yet in the middle we're talking about
a matter of טומאה, tuma, of defilement or impurity, and then going
back to שבועה. shvua. The verses in the middle are what's called
סתום, satum, they're
unclear. And trying trying to figure out what are we talking about?
For some reason, I have the imagery from visiting the Intel Museum.
I don't know, take it or leave it.
The Intel Museum? I didn't know they had a museum.
They have a museum in Santa Clara in the Silicon Valley. Wow.
Because the people are dressed in a full gown, right, and they're
completely... you don't see what they're doing. And they're dealing with tiny
particles, tiny things, and then somehow we get, whatever, a computer, a
phone, right, all the modern technology. And the minutia of things is
super super important even though for somebody who's looking from the outside,
we don't exactly know, I don't know what's going on.
So it... I don't know why it came, but so a little
bit like that, we're dealing with things that are סתומים, stumim, that
are very hard to figure out and then we're trying to unpack
them in different ways in order to come at the end to
a conclusion, what exactly are we talking about in this middle, in
these middle פסוקים. psukim. And so we're now back to the bottom
of ו עמוד ב, vav amud bet, we're picking up the משנה
mishna that says את שיש בה ידיעה בתחילה. et sheyesh ba yediah
betchila. So again, this is a situation where there's knowledge in the
beginning, knowledge in the end, and some העלם, he'elam, some obscure, a
lack of awareness in the middle.
תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, מניין שאין הכתוב מדבר אלא בטומאת מקדש וקדשיו.
minayin she'ein hakatuv medaber ela betumat mikdash vekodashav. How do we know
that when the גמרא gemara talks about these פסוקים psukim here in
the middle, they talk about nothing else but the defiling, the impurity
or טומאה tuma of the מקדש mikdash and its קדשים, kodshim, its
sacrificial foods? We're picking up at the bottom of ו עמוד ב.
vav amud bet. ודין הוא. vedin hu.
So the גמרא gemara says, "It's logical," whether it is or not,
or or it's דין. din. הואיל והזהיר וענש על הטומאה וחיב קרבן
על הטומאה מה כשהזהיר וענש על הטומאה לא הזהיר וענש אלא על
טומאת מקדש וקדשיו אף כשחיב קרבן על הטומאה לא חיב אלא על
טומאת מקדש וקדשיו.
hoil vehizhir veanash al hatuma vechiyav korban al hatuma ma kshehizhir veanash
al hatuma lo hizhir veanash ela al tumat mikdash vekodashav af kshechiyav
korban al hatuma lo chiyav ela al tumat mikdash vekodashav. Simple, completely
completely simple. What are we saying? We're looking at two two different
things, right, the התראה, hatraa, like the warning,
something that was forbidden, and something that had a prescribed punishment. And
טומאה tuma has these things. If somebody intentionally defiled things that are
connected to the temple, then they have both the אזהרה, azhara, הזהיר,
וענש, hiz’hir ve-anash וחיב קרבן על הטומאה, vechiyav korban al hatuma, and
one that does that is liable to bring an offering.
But they don't all come together, meaning if you did it במזיד,
bemezid, you don't bring a קרבן. korban.
This was the beginning of it. If right now we're on a
ידיעה yediah that has a העלם. he'elam. As soon as there is
a העלם, he'elam, it takes us out of the מזיד mezid category.
And so now that's where we are.
Okay, be patient with me, this is not easy. So okay, back,
now I've lost my space. Okay. Since, let me read that.
Since the Torah has explicitly prohibited and prescribed the punishment,
so we have both אזהרה azhara and a punishment, for the intentional
causing טומאה, tuma, right, defilement of something that's sacred, and at that
case made somebody liable to bring an
offering, right, for something that is בשוגג, beshogeg, something that is not
במזיד, bemezid, then it follows that just
as מה כשהזהיר וענש על הטומאה... ma kshehizhir veanash al hatuma... טומאת
מקדש וקודשיו. tumat mikdash ve-kodashav. We learn from it that this is
only relevant to the defilement, the טומאה tumah of the temple and
the קודשים kodashim and the sacrificial food. So too, when it rendered
one liable to bring an offering for the defiling of something sacred,
it rendered one liable to do so only for things that are
not במזיד, bemezid, things that are בשוגג beshogeg for causing טומאה tumah
in the temple and its קודשיו. kodashav. Since we have another עמוד
amud and a half ahead of us dealing with it, so this
I'm good with it.
This is the we might have to go the whole loop around
in order to come to the same place, but give us a
few minutes. Okay. ואימא טומאה, ve-eima tumah, so now what about maybe
this also includes the טומאה? tumah? Because also in the טומאה tumah
we have a situation that הזהיר וענש hiz’hir ve-anash.
that there was a warning, right, the prohibition and a prescribed punishment.
לא אשכחן עוון מיתה דחייב עליה קרבן. lo ash’kahan avon mitah de-chayav
aleha korban. Let's see.
In the case of the טומאה, tumah, and I marked some of
the פסוקים pesukim here so we have them available in the תנ"ך.
Tanakh. In the case of the טומאה, tumah, we have a מיתה
בידי שמיים mitah bi-yedei shamayim as the punishment, a death in the
hands of heaven, which is different from the כרת. karet. כרת, karet,
one we don't exactly know what it means, and two, it punishes
the future generations. And the מיתה בידי שמיים mitah bi-yedei shamayim for
somebody to be dying in the hands of heaven, I don't know
what to do with it because sooner or later we all die
in the hands of heaven, no? Not sure what the Torah means
by it, but maybe unusual death?
Well, it means, it just means an early death as opposed to
כרת karet that, you know, from what I understood the כרת karet
might be is that if, the way the rabbis view it, that
if you have kids, you know, they'll die, you know, early, and
if you don't have kids you won't have kids, חס וחלילה. chas
ve-chalila. You know, that's the way I've typically
right, right, but like
we should never make it like we understand those calculations.
Sure, but there has to be a difference between כרת karet and
מיתה בידי שמיים mitah bi-yedei shamayim because they're not the same thing,
they're not the כרת karet affects, affects the future generation. Right. The
מיתה בידי שמיים mitah bi-yedei shamayim affects only just you, only affects
the person. Okay. Okay,
so the תרומה terumah also has these qualifications of הזהיר hizhir, וענש.
veanash, לא אשכחן עוון מיתה דחייב עליה קרבן. lo ash’kahan avon mitah
de-chayav aleha korban. So we do not find this,
a sin whose punishment for intentional violation is death with regards to
which one is liable to bring an offering. So it's going to
try to compare and contrast the issue of the תרומה, terumah, whether
תרומה terumah is part of it or not. Okay. אימא הני מילי
קרבן קבוע. eima hanei milei korban kavua. So maybe this say that
this statement only applies to a קרבן קבוע. korban kavua. And we're
not talking about a קרבן קבוע. korban kavua. We're talking about קרבן
עולה ויורד korban oleh ve-yored as the גמרא Gemara tells us. אבל
קרבן עולה ויורד מיתי, aval korban oleh ve-yored meiti,
you
say? מדי דהוה אשמיעת קול ובביטוי שפתיים. midei de-hava a-sh'miat kol u-vi-vitui
sefatayim. But the גמרא Gemara calls it the sliding scale offering, the
קרבן עולה ויורד, korban oleh ve-yored, which is a קרבן korban that
is according to one's means. Whether one is rich or poor or
extremely poor, you can bring a different קרבן, korban, and that's the
קרבן korban that's being discussed in the ויקרא Vayikra pay.
One can bring this קרבן עולה ויורד korban oleh ve-yored sliding scale
offering for the violation בשגגה bi-sh'gagah in unintentional
of a transgression that the intentional violation would be כרת. karet. So
again, if we have a violation that we have a warning and
the punishment would be כרת, karet, would be being cut off for
future generations, if this was done intentionally, then when it was done
unintentionally one can bring a קרבן עולה ויורד. korban oleh ve-yored. Where
is it? Not all כרת karet things we can bring קרבן עולה
ויורד, korban oleh ve-yored, right, when we do them unintentionally. So we're
looking for a specific situation. And here we come back to the
פסוק pasuk אשמיעת קול ובביטוי שפתיים. a-sh'miat kol u-vi-vitui sefatayim.
So what we're seeing is, that's what I understand, is what we're
saying is that
טומאת מקדש
וקדשיו,
tumat mikdash
ve-kodashav, there's different קרבנות korbanot than what you do for תרומה, terumah,
so therefore it can't be talking about תרומה. terumah.
Is that what you're trying to say? It will, okay, what I
understand is that תרומה terumah could be included in this situation of
if... If you eat תרומה Terumah intentionally with a warning, you will
have מיתה בידי שמים, Mita bidei Shamayim, right? Different from כרת. Karet.
What if you do it בשגגה? Bishgaga? Could it be that also
for תרומה Terumah you will be able to bring
קרבן
עולה
ויורד?
Korban Oleh
ve-Yored?
Okay, not the Mishnah says that there are three cases where you
would bring one, and that's the third one mentioned, eating תרומה? Terumah?
Yeah, in 5:3, look at 5:3, the person who is impure and
eats of the...
Yeah, no, I'm
talking about the רש"י.
Rashi. I'm talking about the תרומה Terumah part though.
Oh, I'm sorry, I thought it said the opposite.
No, I'm just
asking, like, what are they... Oh, I'm sorry, here, תרומה, Terumah, I'm
sorry, I was talking about תרומה. Terumah. Okay, okay, okay.
We're at the top of ז עמוד א. Zayin Amud Aleph. אמר
קרא, Amar Kra, now we're going to deal with the תרומה... Terumah...
בה. Bah. בה Bah למיעוטי תרומה. Lemi'utei Terumah. So we're going to...
we're seeing that in the פסוק, Pasuk, sorry, in Leviticus, ויקרא ה
ג, Vayikra Hey Gimmel, in Leviticus 5:3, the פסוק Pasuk says בה,
Bah, through which, so therefore the גמרא Gemara understands it to be
a מיעוט, Mi'ut, some exclusionary statement about תרומה. Terumah. We're not yet
sure what it is and we're not yet sure how it's going
to act, but we are noticing that the verse says through which,
in Hebrew בה, Bah, to exclude somebody who is טמא Tamei who
partakes from the תרומה Terumah and this person might be excluded from
having to bring the קרבן עולה ויורד. Korban Oleh ve-Yored. Tough? Yeah,
so far so good. אימא בה למיעוטי מקדש דלא סגי ליה בקרבן
עולה ויורד עד דמייתי קרבן קבוע.
Eima bah lemi'utei mikdash
dela sagi lei be-korban oleh ve-yored ad demayti korban kavua. Let's see.
The גמרא Gemara asks,
but say the verse, the word בה, Bah, through which, comes to
exclude somebody who makes the temple טמא, Tamei, right, למיעוטי מקדש, Lemi'utei
Mikdash, and teaches...
sorry,
that it's not enough for him to achieve atonement, maybe his transgression
is too severe, with just the קרבן עולה ויורד, Korban Oleh ve-Yored,
with just the sliding scale קרבן. Korban. The only way, עד דמייתי
קרבן קבוע, Ad demayti korban kavua, the only way he can fix,
achieve atonement, is by bringing a קרבן קבוע. Korban Kavua. So now
we're like in a complicated...
right, we just don't know. So what is the בה? Bah? Is
it excluding תרומה Terumah or is it excluding something else?
We don't know. Yes, we don't know what the בה Bah is
excluding,
exactly. קרי רבא להא דרבי דולה מים מבורות עמוקים. Kari Rava le-ha
de-Rabbi doleh mayim mi-borot amukim. Beautiful.
רבא Rava is going to say about רבי יהודה הנשיא Rabbi Yehuda
HaNasi who's going to try to explain this construct to us, one
who draws water from deep wells. He brings a פסוק Pasuk from
Proverbs to say this is super complicated, hence my issue with
high-tech people dealing with tiny, minute things that eventually create something big.
And רבי Rabbi is going to bring us something from a deep
insight to try to explain it, okay?
דתניא, Detanya, we're going to bring a ברייתא Braita to try to
explain this verse.
Okay. דתניא רבי אומר אקרא אני חיה בהמה חיה בהמה למה נאמרה.
Detanya Rabbi omer akra ani chaya behema chaya behema lama neemra. In
the פסוקים Psukim in front of us in ויקרא, Vayikra, both words
are mentioned, חיה Chaya and בהמה. Behema. Quick translation: animal, but a
חיה Chaya is considered a non-domesticated animal and בהמה Behema is a
domesticated animal. חיה, Chaya,
non-domesticated,
impure. In a פסוק Pasuk he's saying that, it's talking about
in the פסוק Pasuk we're on. And that's not חיה Chaya is
impure.
Yeah, there are kosher חיה, Chaya, of course.
Like a deer?
Like a deer would be a kosher חיה, Chaya, but here we're
trying to talk about בהמה טמאה Behema Tmeiah and trying to compare
the two. Okay. So חיה, Chaya, it says already חיה, Chaya, בהמה
למה נאמרה? Behema lama neemra? נאמר כאן בהמה טמאה ונאמר להלן בהמה
טמאה. Neemar kan behema tmeiah ve-neemar le-halan behema tmeiah. Where is the
כאן Kan and the להלן? Le-halan? So there's two places where בהמה
Behema is going to be said. One is... okay, so let's say
this expression comes. רבי יהודה הנשיא Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi says, since domesticated
animal is also referred to as a חיה, Chaya, it would be
enough, right, if we just say חיה. Chaya. Why does it say
בהמה? Behema?
The comparison is with ויקרא ז
כא,
Vayikra Zayin
Kaf-Aleph, should be one of the marked ones. In ויקרא ז כא...
Vayikra Zayin Kaf-Aleph...
21,
what is the פסוק pasuk? *pasuk*? Also says בהמה טמאה *behemah temeah*.
Yes, but it only says בהמה *behemah*, doesn't say חיה *chayah*.
Right, only says בהמה טמאה *behemah temeah*, and it talks about the
somebody who intentionally defiles an offering by partaking from it while
he's impure, right? Yes. So we bring those two together, בהמה טמאה
*behemah temeah* here, בהמה טמאה *behemah temeah* there, and we say just
as below, just as here, it refers as it says in the
גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*, back in the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*, מה להלן טומאת
קודש tumat kodesh. אף כאן טומאת קודש *mah le-hallan tumat kodesh af
kan tumat kodesh*. Just like this in 7:21
it says, it refers to the טומאה tumah *tumah* of the קודש
*kodesh*, here also it refers to the טומאה tumah *tumah* of the
קודש *kodesh*. Not yet the קדשים kodshim. *kodshim*, the קדשים kodshim, *kodshim*,
not yet the מקדש Mikdash? *Mikdash*. אשכחן טומאת קודש טומאת מקדש Mikdash,
מנלן *ashkechan tumat kodesh tumat mikdash minalan*. So this is רבי Rabbi
*Rebbi*'s way of explaining how the בהמה טמאה *behemah temeah* connects for
us the טומאה tumah *tumah* of the מקדש Mikdash, *Mikdash* here and
there. How now do we connect, no sorry, backwards, connects for us
the טומאה tumah, *tumah* of the קדשים kodshim, *kodshim*. How now we
connect the טומאה tumah *tumah* of the מקדש Mikdash. *Mikdash*? In order
to connect the טומאה tumah *tumah* of the מקדש mikdash, *Mikdash*, we're
going to bring a different פסוק pasuk. *pasuk*. טומאת מקדש mikdash. מנלן
אמר קרא בכל קודש לא תגע ואל המקדש לא תבוא *tumat mikdash
minalan amar kra be-chol kodesh lo tiga ve-el ha-mikdash lo tavo*. איתקש
מקדש mikdash, לקודש *itkesh mikdash le-kodesh*. The פסוק pasuk *pasuk* that's now
being given, also marked, is from ויקרא Vayikra *Vayikra* 12:4. This
is the opening of פרשת תזריע *Parashat Tazria* with the יולדת *yoledet*.
About the יולדת *yoledet*, it says בכל קודש לא תגע ואל המקדש
לא תבוא *be-chol kodesh lo tiga ve-el ha-mikdash lo tavo*. She can't
touch any of the, right, קדשים kodshim, *kodshim* of the sacred items,
and she can also not come into the מקדש *Mikdash*. Therefore, we
juxtapose the Temple to the sacred items in the פרשת
תזריע *Parashat Tazria*, and so from there we learn that they are
connected. Okay? Okay.
But we still haven't, so now we know that the קדשים kodshim,
*kodshim* and the קדושת מקדש *kedushat mikdash* are connected, but we still
don't know how the תרומה trumah? *terumah* fits into this puzzle.
אי הכי
תרומה trumah; נמי *i hachi
terumah nami*? And there
should be the תוספות *Tosafot* that says that it's not like what
about, what about the תרומה trumah *terumah*?
Because we're trying to figure out if this is more expansive, right?
Is it בכל *be-chol* including תרומה terumah? *terumah* or is it excluding
something else? Like oh well, you know, we're learning from another פסוק
*pasuk* that טומאת מקדש וקודש *tumat mikdash ve-kodesh* is linked. So therefore
it must be טומאת מקדש וקודש *tumat mikdash ve-kodesh*. But wait, maybe
we can explain the verse is referring to תרומה *terumah* as well?
In which case it's back to our original question.
Right. So we're trying to see if the תרומה *terumah* excludes or
includes. And just heads up, like, the תרומה *terumah* situation is what's
called a מיעוט miut. *mi'ut*, right? It tries to isolate something. And
we're, I don't know if you need like a bird's view and
then go into the details, a מיעוט miut *mi'ut* by itself can
exclude something. But if a מיעוט *mi'ut* comes with another מיעוט *mi'ut*,
it's like minus times minus creates a plus. And so it creates
the opposite, and that's eventually what we'll get to. It'll just take
us a long roundabout journey. But that's basically what we're trying to
see. Are we talking about just that the קרבן עולה ויורד korban
oleh ve-yored *Korban Oleh Ve-Yored*, the sliding scale offering, is good only
for the טומאת מקדש וקדשיו tum'at mikdash vekadashav. *tumat mikdash ve-kodashav*, the
defilement of the Temple and its קדשים *kodshim*, or also where is
the תרומה *terumah* could fit here, does it fit here? Okay. אי
הכי תרומה נמי דאמר מר בכל קודש לא תגע לרבות את התרומה
*i hachi terumah nami de-amar mar be-chol kodesh lo tiga lerabbot et
ha-terumah*. So opinion one: maybe this was said about a יולדת *yoledet*,
right? She can't touch any of the קדשים *kodshim*. That means any,
to include the תרומה *terumah* in the prohibition. Right? So it should
include the תרומה *terumah* in the קרבן עולה ויורד korban oleh ve-yored?
*Korban Oleh Ve-Yored*. Maybe at the end I'll understand what it is.
הא מיעט רחמנא בה *ha mi'et rachmana bah*. So we see the
גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* explains that השם *Hashem*, the תורה Torah *Torah*, right,
the text,
excludes something with this term because of this little tiny word in
the middle of this ויקרא Vayikra *Vayikra* 5:3, which is the פסוק
*pasuk* that is the basis of what we're dealing. Okay. אימא בא
ba למיעוטי מקדש מסתברא מקדש לא ממעטינן שכן בכרת כמותה *eima ba
le-miyutei mikdash mistabra mikdash lo mematinan sheken be-karet kemotah*. Should we say
that the term בה *bah* serves to exclude the טומאה tumah *tumah*
of the מקדש *Mikdash*? So it'd be the מיעוט should address the
מקדש? No, says the גמרא, Gemara it is reasonable that we should
not exclude the טומאה of the מקדש, the defilement of the temple,
because an intentional punishment is because its intentional punishment violation
is punishable by כרת karet just like the קדשים. And what is
the problem with תרומה? We did not see a punishment by כרת
karet with תרומה; we see a punishment by
מיתה שבידי שמיים. mita she-bidei shamayim. Okay. אדרבה, adra-ba, תרומה לא ממעטינן
שכן אכילה כמותה. truma lo mematinan she-ken achila kemotah. No, counterargument, on
the contrary, we should not exclude the one who's eating the תרומה
when he's טמא tamei because that is,
wait, sorry, maybe there is a different way to deal with it
because of the eating, שכן אכילה כמותה, she-ken achila kemotah, similar to
one that's eating the קדשים, the sacrificial food.
Right, as opposed to going to the מקדש, you're not eating anything,
you're just טמא tamei and going to a place.
Right. So still no proof that one is liable to bring this
קרבן עולה ויורד korban oleh ve-yored
for the temple, for defiling the temple. Okay, אלא, ela, we're going
to try to bring our proof now from somewhere else. אלא אמר
רבא שלש כריתות בשלמים למה? ela amar Rava shalosh kritot bishlamim lama?
There are three situations where שלמים shlamim offering is one can get
כרת karet for eating it inappropriately.
I think it means it's said three times, right?
It says it three times with שלמים shlamim and כרת karet are
said three times. So what is why do I need the three
times? אחת לכלל ואחת לפרט ואחת
לטומאה הכתובה בתורה סתם ואיני יודע מה היא. achat lichlal ve-achat lifrat
ve-achat le-tumah ha-ktuva ba-Torah stam ve-eini yodeia ma hi. That's the most
comforting sentence in the גמרא, Gemara I think. If רבא Rava can
say one is for general, one is for general case of ritually
impure person, one is for specific instance of somebody eating שלמים, shlamim,
and one I don't know what it is for, it is something
in the תורה that is not mentioned here. Therefore, it seems like
we have one free one that maybe we can use to apply
to understanding what we're talking with us what we're talking about here.
Okay. הוי אומר טומאת קדש ואם אינו ענין לטומאת קדש דנפקא ליה
מדרבי תנא הוא ענין לטומאת מקדש. hevei omer tumat kodesh ve-im eino
inyan le-tumat kodesh denafkah lei mi-de-Rabbi tana hu inyan le-tumat mikdash. If
it's not for the קדשים, maybe it's for the מקדש. Let's try
to unpack it a little bit better.
Okay.
So now we have one passage
that describes a טומאה of something sacred, right, of a קדש kodesh
without specifying the situation. Is this קרבן עולה ויורד? korban oleh ve-yored
Therefore, you must say that the third mention of this כרת karet
that goes with the שלמים shlamim has to do with טומאה of
sacrificial foods, of קדשים, but if it is not needed to teach
this, because if we already know that the other thing the קרבן
עולה ויורד korban oleh veyored from somewhere else, as that we've already
learned from רבי Rebi with the
then we can apply it to defiling the temple. If we don't
need it for food, for the קדשים, maybe we can apply it
to the temple. Accordingly, one who intentionally makes the temple טמא tamei
when
because they enter it when they're impure, when they're in a state
of טומאה, is going to get כרת, karet, right, one who does
intentionally
intentional defilement of the temple is going to get כרת. karet. And
it's reasonable that he should be liable to bring this קרבן עולה
ויורד korban oleh veyored, if he does that unintentionally, בשגגה. bi-shgaga. Back
to the גמרא. Gemara והאי, ve-hai, this is actually the the רבא's
Rava statement, I think is from the ברייתא. braita. The גמרא Gemara
is going to try to unpack it again. Hold on one second.
והאי מיבעי ליה לכדרבי אבהו דאמר רבי אבהו שלש כריתות בשלמים למה
אחת לכלל אחת לפרט ואחת לדברים שאינם נאכלים. ve-hai miba'ei lei le-khed-Rabbi
Abahu de-amar Rabbi Abahu shalosh kritot bishlamim lama achat lichlal achat lifrat
ve-achat lidvarim she-einam ne-echalim. He says
so say
this is not for something I don't know, the third one is
for things that can't be eaten.
That's the third one of the כרת karet with the שלמים shlamim
that I don't know what to do with. or for things that
are generally not eaten like, I don't know, certain, they give example,
certain kind of incense that normally one will not eat. ורבי שמעון
*Ve-Rabbi Shimon* offers us a slightly different. רבי שמעון דאמר דברים שאינן
נאכלים אין חייבים עליהם כרת karet משום טומאה לאיתויי חטאת chatat, הפנימית
*Rabbi Shimon de-amar devarim she-einan ne'echalim ein chayavim aleihem karet mishum tumah
l'atuyei chatat hapnimit*. So
רגע rega, *rega*, things that,
items that are not generally eaten, one is not liable to be
punished with כרת *karet* for taking them. That would be like almost
crazy if we say that something that normally is not eaten, whatever
you eat from,
bring example of some of the קטורת *ketoret* or something, you're not
supposed to eat it, but you also are not going to get
כרת *karet* for it, right? It's not liable to be punished with
כרת *karet* for eating them when somebody is טמא tamei *tamei*.
So, takes us back again to the same place. The third mention
is necessary, the third mention of the שלמים *shelamim* and the כרת
*karet*, to include the case of an impure person who eats an
internal sin offering. What is the internal? This is the שעיר הפנימי
*sa'ir hapnimi*. On יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur*, we have the
שעיר לעזאזל *sa'ir la-azazel* and one שעיר *sa'ir* who is the שעיר
הפנימי *sa'ir hapnimi*. As it could enter, it could enter your mind,
not could enter the temple, you could think סלקא דעתך *salka da-atach*
that רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* says for any type of offering that
is not sacrificed on
and the blood applied to the external altar like the שלמים *shelamim*,
like the peace offering, one cannot be liable to be punished with
כרת *karet* for eating it if it is פיגול
*pigul*,
if it is eating such an offering that was sacrificed with a
different intent.
Wait, wait, wait, isn't eating פיגול *pigul* כרת *karet* if you do
it deliberately?
I don't know, let me see.
Yes, it says כרת *karet*.
כרת *karet* for the פיגול *pigul*, Leviticus 7:18.
How
do
we put this together? So maybe that's already taken and it doesn't
help us answer our issue. Since
even if you
eat it with, it
says one might have thought that similarly for such an offering, one
is also not liable to be punished with כרת *karet* for intentionally
eating it when ritually impure. The third mention then teaches us that
one is liable. Therefore, there is still no proof that one is
liable for the קרבן עולה ויורד korban oleh veyored, *korban oleh ve-yored*
since these other things are covered maybe with the כרת *karet* and
yeah then.
So why would I have thought that you would not be חייב
כרת *chayav karet* for eating פיגול *pigul* if it were
טהור *tahor* טמא tamei *tamei*? It shouldn't matter, you should be כרת
*karet*. I don't get this.
I'm not sure I could do any more justice to it. Maybe
Rabbi Linzker can help with this tomorrow, but I'm not sure I
can do any more with it at this point.
It's all over מסכת זבחים פיגול *masechet Zevachim pigul*.
Right, right, and they do mention it.
Yeah, sorry, I didn't finish reading that. It said the inner חטאת
chatat, *chatat* is not included in the law of פיגול *pigul*.
I think we'll just have to
let that go.
The internal חטאת *chatat* of the שעיר *sa'ir*.
Well, of course not, it's not eaten at all.
Right, it says primary applications of blood.
Or it has to do with the, with the awareness, or it
has to go back to the ידיעות *yedi'ot*. Did they know? Did
they know and then not know, etc.?
I mean פיגול *pigul* applies to a קרבן korban, *korban* that's going
to be at least partially eaten. Okay, so the,
I don't think it applies.
So maybe that's why it doesn't apply. Okay. I'm going to continue
for the sake of time and more confusion on the next thing.
Okay. We're going to try to explain it in a different way.
Yes, you can see other people are not satisfied with it. אלא
אמרי נהרדעי משמיה דרבא *Ela amrei Nahardei mishmei de-Rava*. שלוש טומאות בשלמים
למה *Shalosh tumot bi-shlamim lama*? Now a different way of trying to
explain why we have three טומאות *tumot* in issue of שלמים *shelamim*.
Why? אחת לכלל ואחת לפרט *Achat lichlal ve-achat lifrat*, everybody agrees, ואחת
לטומאה הכתובה בתורה סתם ואיני יודע מהי *ve-achat le-tumah haktuvah ba-Torah stam
ve-eini yodeia mahi*. So we're going back to the נהרדעי *Nahardei* says
in the name of רבא *Rava*, same thing that we just saw
רבא *Rava* saying,
but now with a difference, not כרת *karet* but טומאות *tumot*. There's
three
situations of somebody being טמא tame, *tamei*, ritual impure status with regards
to somebody who eats the peace offering and the third one we
still. are not sure what that is. הוי אומר טומאת קודש. So
now maybe it's available for us for the defilement of the קודשים
kodashim of the food.
ואם אינו עניין לטומאת קודש דנפקא ליה מדרבי תנהו עניין לטומאת מקדש.
Veim eino inyan letumat kodesh denafka lei midrebi tanahu inyan letumat mikdash.
Okay, if רבי already explained to us the חיה ובהמה chaya uveheima
earlier, then maybe
apply it to the matter of the temple. If we can't apply
it to the matter of the קודשים, kodashim, maybe apply it to
the matter of the temple. והאי נמי מיבעי ליה Vehai nami mibayei
lei and that third mention is also necessary. אידי דבעי למכתב כרת
Idi dibayei lemichtav karet לדרבי אבהו כתב נמי טמאות דלא סגי ליה
בלאו הכי. Ledrebi Abahu katav nami tumeos delo sagi lei belav hachi.
Because
since it is necessary for the Torah to write the כרת punishment
three times in order to expound it in accordance with the statement
of רבי אבהו, Rebi Abahu, it also has to write that the
person was ritual impure, as it is not sufficient to mention the
punishment without mentioning for what the punishment was given.
Still, no proof that one is liable to bring the קרבן korban
עולה ויורד for
unintentionally defiling the temple.
Okay, we're going to try to...
תא שמע... Ta shema... there. We're going to try to find it
from a different place and the פסוקים pesukim are marked. אלא אמר
רבא אתיא טומאתו טומאתו כתיב הכא לכל טומאתו. Ela amar Rava atya
tumato tumato ksiv hacha lechol tumato.
Okay, let's try another word that we can maybe derive from a
word analogy between two פסוקים. pesukim. One is the word טומאתו tumato
which appears in our פסוקים pesukim in Leviticus 5:3 and כתיב התם
ksiv hatam in במדבר Bamidbar 19:13 which is the פרה אדומה, parah
adumah, also it says טמא יהיה עוד טומאתו בו. tamei yihye od
tumato bo. If you would like the תנ"ך, Tanach, it's... מה להלן
טומאת מקדש אף כאן טומאת מקדש.
Mah lehalan tumat mikdash af
kan tumat mikdash.
Now maybe we can do a גזרה שוה gezeira shava between the
פסוקים pesukim we have in front of us in ויקרא Vayikra 5
and between the פסוקים pesukim in פרה אדומה. parah adumah.
Okay. And just as the verse there in Numbers refers to the
מקדש, so too the קרבן עולה ויורד, the sliding scale offering, is
brought to atone for the מקדש. The גמרא Gemara asks: but if
so, ואלא בא למה לי. veela ba lamah li. So fine, we're
good with the קודשים, kodashim, we're good with the מקדש, but what
should we do with the
תרומה? The גמרא Gemara answers: לרבות נבלת עוף טהור. lerabbot nevelat of
tahor. The בא ba includes one that is impure by eating a
non-kosher
carcass of
a kosher bird—no, incorrectly
slaughtered carcass of a kosher bird.
Tyson or Perdue chicken? Huh? Tyson or Perdue chicken?
Okay. Those are things that I maybe don't know
about. Okay. הא אמרת בא מיעוטא הוא משום דמיעוטא הוא איצטריך כתיב
או כי יגע בדבר.
Ha amrat ba miuta hu mishum demiuta hu itztarich
ksiv o ki yiga bedavar. So, wait. But didn't you say that
the term בא ba is a restriction? Right, we said that the
בא ba, is unnecessary and it comes to create a מיעוט. How
can you now use it to include additional cases? Is it a
מיעוט or not? הגמרא Hagemara explains... wait, I can do both. It
is precisely because it is a restriction that it includes additional
cases. או כי יגע בדבר. O ki yiga bedavar. נגיעה אין דלאו
בר נגיעה לא. Negia in delav bar negia lo.
This is about the touching indicates one who is טמא tame with
any form of impurity that can give impurity through touching, yes, applicable,
he is defiling the temple
through his טמא status, but one that is impure with some form
of טומאה that cannot be transmitted through touching, he cannot be liable.
Therefore,
conclusion, וכתיב בא מיעוטא הוה מיעוט אחר מיעוט ואין מיעוט אחר מיעוט
אלא לרבות. uchtiv ba miuta hava miut achar miut veein miut achar
miut ela lerabbot. So therefore the verse starts with a restriction, בא,
ba, and then the verse continues with... sorry, the restriction is... first
restriction was
maybe
the יגע בדבר yiga bedavar and the next restriction is the בא,
and now we have a restriction on top of a restriction. If
we have a restriction on a
restriction... My understanding is just
if
you have a limitation upon a limitation it is meant to only
include.
Yeah. Right.
This concludes our discussion about the
עת שיש בה ידיעה בתחילה. et sheyesh ba yediah batchila. This concludes
the discussion about a case that has knowledge in the beginning, knowledge
in the end, and a העלם he'elam and a no-knowledge in the
middle.
So then what do we make of it? That the tumah is
included or
not included? I think it's only, I think at the end we're
proving what we set out in the beginning, that it only is
the
טומאת מקדש וקדשיו. It only has to do with unintentional defilement of
the temple and the kodshim and the food in it,
and the tumah
included with it, I would go with that.
They quote Rambam, Rambam has said this is not explicit in the
Torah but that this is learned as a
tradition.
Okay, this was the whole beginning that it says ודינו וסברא vedino
usvara like this is our understanding. We have פסוקים pesukim that we
don't understand with other פסוקים pesukim we don't understand and we're trying
to make sense out of them together.
We stand on all fours, actually more than on all fours, we
got
right back where we started. Okay, let's do a little bit more.
Now, יש בידיעה בתחילה ואין בידיעה בסוף. yesh biyediah batchila ve'ein biyediah
basof.
Now we have a situation with awareness in the beginning and no
knowledge in the end.
So when the person will know, when the person will be aware,
they will be liable for the קרבן עולה ויורד, for the sliding
scale
קרבן, right, offering? But as long as they don't know, this not
knowing is indefinite. It can go on forever. So how do we
atone for it? For this we atone with שעיר הנעשה בפנים. sa'ir
hana'aseh bifnim. That's back to the משנה, mishna,
the not scapegoat, what is it called, goat I guess, the goat
that is sacrificed inside goat, and
יום כיפור Yom Kippur, itself, they atone. Where is our פסוק? I'm
going to read you the whole פסוק. The פסוק is from ויקרא
Vayikra 16:16. Yeah, it's יום כיפור, Yom Kippur
it's the יום כיפור reading: וכפר על הקדש מטמאת בני ישראל ומפשעיהם
לכל חטאתם וכן יעשה לאהל מועד השוכן אתם בתוך טמאתם. vechiper al
hakodesh mitumot benei yisrael umipisheihem lechol chatotam vechen ya'aseh leohel mo'ed hashochen
itam betoch tumotam.
And he shall
atone the קדש kodesh from the transgressions or uncleanness, from the טמאות
tumot of בני ישראל Benei Yisrael and פשעיהם לכל
חטאתם. pisheihem lechol chatotam. And we're going to see that the גמרא
Gemara. is trying to unpack two issues here: one is the connection
between פשע pesha and חטאת, intentional, not intentional, and what is this
מ mem doing there in the beginning? If he is atoning from
טמאות בני ישראל, tumot benei yisrael, מטמאות בני ישראל mitumot benei yisrael
ומפשעיהם. umipisheihem.
He should just atone for all the טמאות tumot and all the
פשעים, pesha'im, right? But there is a little מ mem and we'll
see that we're going to have great fun with it. Okay, so
what are we talking about? What are the טמאות בני ישראל tumot
benei yisrael that this might include? גמרא tells us: יש לי בעניין
זה להביא שלוש טמאות טומאת עבודה זרה וטומאת גילוי עריות וטומאת שפיכות
דמים. yesh li be'inyan ze lehavi shalosh tumot tum'at avodah zarah vetum'at
giluy arayot vetum'at shefichut damim. Three classic sins can be atoned in
this situation: עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, גילוי עריות, giluy arayot, ושפיכות דמים.
shefichut damim.
Idolatry,
forbidden sexual relationships, and killing somebody, murder. רגע,
don't go away yet. First we need פסוקים pesukim to connect the
טומאה to these three issues. בעבודה זרה הוא אומר: be'avodah zarah hu
omer: למען טמא מקדשי. lema'an tame mikdashi.
I did not mark all those, but in עבודה זרה avodah zarah
this is a case in ויקרא 20 where the one gives their
son to the מולך, Molech, so it says טמא, the word טמא
appears. ובגילוי עריות ubegiluy arayot in ויקרא 18: ושמרתם את משמרתי לבלתי
עשות מחקות התועבת וגו' ולא תטמאו בהם. ushmartem et mishmarti levilti asot
michukot hato'evot velo titame'u bahem.
So the word טומאה is there. ובשפיכות דמים הוא אומר ubeshfichut damim
hu omer in במדבר: Bamidbar: ולא תטמא את הארץ. velo tetame et
ha'aretz.
So...
The three טומאות *tumot* I am asking, יכול על שלוש טומאות הללו
יהא שעיר מכפר *Yachol al shalosh tumot halalu yehei sa'ir mechaper*? Is
it possible that the שעיר *sa'ir*, so you could do all these
things בשגגה *bishgegah*,
and then the שעיר *sa'ir* of יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* atones all
these things? תלמוד לומר *Talmud lomar*, and what we just pointed out
in ויקרא *Vayikra* 16:16, מטומאות בני ישראל *mitumot b'nei Yisrael* ולא כל
טומאות בני ישראל *v'lo kol tumot b'nei Yisrael*. It should have said
this will atone for everything, but it is only, it just says
some from the impurities of the children of Israel. So which one?
We are going to try to quickly, not quickly we are okay,
unpack which טומאה *tumah* are we talking about? And we are just
beginning, we are not going to be able to finish it. מה
מצינו שחלק הכתוב מכלל כל טומאות *Mah matzinu she'chilek hakatuv miklal kol
tumot*? So now, we have to look for some place where a
טומאה *tumah* was differentiated, was separated out. Where is that case? The
case we just saw. הוי אומר טומאת מקדש וקדשיו אף כאן בטומאת
מקדש וקדשיו *Hevei omer tumat mikdash v'kodshav af kan b'tumat mikdash v'kodshav*.
This is according to רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*, where the שעיר *sa'ir*
does not atone for everything, for all the טומאות *tumot*, just מטומאות
*mitumot*. Which one? The טומאה *tumah* of the מקדש *Mikdash* and קדשיו
*kodshav*. If somebody knew initially that they are impure or that they
are doing something wrong, but for some reason that awareness escaped them
and was never regained, this is a specific situation we are here.
רבי יהודה
*Rabbi Yehuda* learned it, as we just saw, from this מה מצינו
*mah matzinu*, from comparing two different פסוקים *pesukim*. רבי שמעון אומר ממקומו
הוא מוכרע *Rabbi Shimon omer mimkomo hu muchra*. Rabbi Shimon says you
can learn it from the פסוק *pasuk* right here, you don't need
to compare the טומאה *tumah* to a different place. הרי הוא אומר
וכיפר על הקודש *harei hu omer v'chiper al hakodesh*. So we have
a mention of קודש *kodesh*. מטומאות *mitumot*, מטומאות של קודש *mitumot shel
kodesh*, like פשוט *pashut*, very פשוט *pashut*. From the, from the פסוק
*pasuk*, על הקודש *al hakodesh* already mentioned. מטומאות *mitumot*, so just something
that is being differentiated, excluded out, so that means the טומאת מקדש
וקדשיו *tumat mikdash v'kodshav*. I.e. שעיר פנימי *sa'ir pnimi* is the inside
goat atones for the טומאת מקדש וקדשיו *tumat mikdash v'kodshav*. יכול על
כל טומאה שבקודש יהא שעיר זה מכפר *Yachol al kol tumah she'bakodesh
yehei sa'ir zeh mechaper*? Is it possible then that for everything that
one does wrong unintentionally with the temple and the קדשים *kodshim* could
the שעיר *sa'ir* be atoning for that? תלמוד לומר ומפשעיהם לכל חטאתם
*Talmud lomar u'mipisheihem l'chol chatatam*. חטאים דומיא דפשעים *chata'im dumya d'pish'aim*. חטאים
*chata'im* are like פשעים *pish'aim*. מה פשעים שאינם בני קרבן אף חטאים
שאינם בני קרבן *mah pish'aim she'einam b'nei korban af chata'im she'einam b'nei
korban*. Okay, so now we specify two things. One we said the
שעיר *sa'ir* is talking about something that has to do with טומאת
מקדש וקדשיו *tumat mikdash v'kodshav*, with the impurity or defiling the מקדש
*Mikdash*, the temple, and the קדשים *kodshim* and the food. But now
it has to be something specific because the sum of the חטאים
*chata'im*, there is a קרבן *korban*. If there is a חטא *chet*
that has knowledge, that we know at some point, then there is
a way to atone for it with a קרבן *korban*. So what,
how do we find the specific situation? We need a פשעים שאינם
בני קרבן וחטאים שאינם בני קרבן *pish'aim she'einam b'nei korban v'chata'im she'einam
b'nei korban*. Let's see if we can find them.
Okay. ומניין ליש בה ידיעה בתחילה ואין בה ידיעה בסוף ששעיר זה
תולה *U'minayin l'yesh bah yedi'ah batchilah v'ein bah yedi'ah basof she'sa'ir zeh
toleh*? Maybe it should be upside down. Maybe it is backward. Maybe
it is something not that has knowledge in the beginning and no
awareness in the end, but rather something that has no awareness in
the beginning but then a knowledge in the end. No, לכל חטאתם
*l'chol chatatam*, something that is חייב חטאת *chayav chatat*. Things that are
liable to bring the sin offering. That is the קרבן עולה ויורד
*korban oleh v'yored*, the sliding scale. This means they should become aware
of the sin. If there is no awareness, then
keeps going until there is awareness. Okay. This was the ברייתא *beraita*.
Now we are going to try to find the גמרא *Gemara* is
going to try to figure out what we are talking about. אמר
רב יש לי בעניין זה להביא ג' טומאות *Amar Rav yesh li
b'inyan zeh l'havi gimel tumot*. Okay, again what we just mentioned. יש
לי בעניין זה להביא ג' טומאות *yesh li b'inyan zeh l'havi gimel
tumot*. טומאת עבודה זרה avodah zarah? וטומאת גילוי עריות gilluy arayot. וטומאת
שפיכות דמים shefikhut damim, *tumat avoda zara v'tumat giluy arayot v'tumat shfichut
damim*. The impurity of idol worship and
forbidden relations and murder.
Okay, wait. Problem, this is a problem. Every time we mention עבודה
זרה, avodah zarah there is punishment that comes with it. So what
is the specific nuance that we're trying to see? האי עבודה זרה
היכי דמי, hai avodah zarah heykhi dami, where is this specific carved
out case in עבודה זרה? avodah zarah. אי במזיד בר קטלא הוא,
אי בשוגג בר קרבנו. ee bemezid bar katla hu, ee beshogeg bar
korbano. If somebody does עבודה זרה intentionally, במזיד, bemezid, then he's subject
to death, right? He gets death penalty
and no קרבן will ever atone for his sin. אי בשוגג בר
קרבנו. ee beshogeg bar korbano. So if he did it by mistake,
he can bring a sacrifice. So where, where is that situation? Ah,
here is a situation where this can apply:
intentional without warning, במזיד ולא התרו ביה, בשוגג ולא אתיידע ליה. bemezid
velo hitru beh, beshogeg velo ityada leh.
So
this atones in a case where one transgresses intentionally but there was
no warning because what we mentioned in the way beginning is for
the punishment to be applicable, you need to have
warning and know the punishment. So here we have intentional but no
warning. Alternatively, alternatively,
we can have the opposite, בשוגג, beshogeg, unintentional and
no knowledge. And then גמרא continues: the same is גילוי עריות. gilluy
arayot גילוי עריות gilluy arayot also, and we're moving to the next
דף daf and pause in just a minute. גילוי עריות also we
have the same situation. If it's intentional, person might be liable by
death. If it's by mistake, then he has to bring a sacrifice.
So what is the specific? במזיד ולא התרו ביה, בשוגג ולא אתיידע
ליה. bemezid velo hitru beh, beshogeg velo ityada leh. It was intentional
but there was no warning. It was or alternatively it was unintentional
and he was not aware. And שפיכות דמים, same situation. If it
was intentional, he should be killed. If he was
בשוגג, beshogeg, he should be exiled and we spend all of מכות
Makkot talking about it. But here is a situation of like no,
it was intentional without warning, it was
unintentional but without awareness. I'm going to pause here on דף ח'
עמוד א', daf chet amud aleph, six lines from the top of
ח' עמוד א', chet amud aleph, and God willing we'll continue with
this גמרא. Thank you.
I just realized I didn't read to the end of the notes
about the חטאת, even the inner one would
be atoning for עבודה זרה.